Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is קע"ה, Kuf Ayin
Hey, בבא בתרא Bava Batra 175, the penultimate דף, daf, and we
pick up with the on קע"ד עמוד ב, Kuf Ayin Dalet Amud
Bet, 174B, about a third of the way down, and
we
are dealing with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel’s statement
in the משנה Mishna after we've discussed the liability of an ערב
arev and whether the responsibility and that they go to him after
you go to the לווה. loveh. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says that if somebody is an ערב arev for a
כתובה, ketubah, which means basically he's guaranteeing the husband's responsibility so that
if there's divorce or death, the wife can collect if she can't
collect from the husband's estate, she can collect from the ערב arev
that and then they get divorced that the basically you have to
insist that the man makes a vow not to remarry his wife
because we're concerned that there's going to be some type of a
scheme in place and he and his wife are in cahoots and
they're going to use this to collect from the ערב arev and
then they'll get remarried. Okay, and nobody really disagrees on that ruling
in the משנה. Mishna. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
It says משה בר עצרי, Moshe bar Atzri, so this person משה
בר עצרי, Moshe bar Atzri, ערבא דכתובתא דכלתיה הוה. arva de’ketuvata de’khalatei
hava. He was the guarantor of his daughter-in-law's כתובה, ketubah, meaning it
would have been more maybe straightforward to say he was the guarantor
for his son's debt, for his son's assumption of responsibility in the
כתובה ketubah for his daughter-in-law. So for his son's wife. רב הונא
בריה, Rav Huna brei, now רב הונא Rav Huna was the son
of this משה בר עצרי, Moshe bar Atzri, צורבא מרבנן הוה, tzurba
me’rabanan hava,
so he was, you know, a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. ודחיקא ליה
מילתא, ve’dachika lei milta, and he was having a hard time financially.
He really couldn't get a good פרנסה parnasa and put food on
the table. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, ליגא ליה
אינש לרב הונא דניגרשה לדביתיה ותיזיל ותיגבי כתובתה מאבוה. leiga lei inash
le-Rav Huna de-neigarsha le-deviteih ve-tei-zeil ve-tigbei ketuvata mei-avuha. So he says, אביי
Abaye said, isn't there anybody around that might could go and
advise רב הונא Rav Huna that what he should do is divorce
his wife and then she can go collect her כתובה ketubah from
her father, means his father, and from the guarantor. והדר נהדרינה, ve-hadar
neihaderana, then he can remarry her. So we have a perfect, somebody
should, אביי Abaye was sort of not taking responsibility, he wasn't going
to be the one to advise, but he was dropping a broad
hint that somebody should go and give him this advice. Now this
seems very troubling that that would be how you would advise somebody
and let's see what the גמרא Gemara says with it. אמר ליה
רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said to him, והאי ידירנה
הנאה תנן? ve-hai yadirana hana’ah tnan? But רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says in the משנה Mishna that he would have
to make a נדר neder not to get הנאה hana’ah from her
to prevent himself from remarrying her. So it's not going to work
anyway. So it's funny that, you know, רבא Rava’s concerned with practically
it wouldn't work, not that there was anything wrong with this idea.
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back to
him,
אטו כל דמגרש בדינא מגרש? attu kol de-megarish dina de-megarish? What, everybody
who divorces his wife does it in a בית דין? Beis Din?
Let him divorce his wife and then there'll be who's to say
that it'll be a public matter? I mean now of course you
wouldn't even think about doing it without a בית דין, Beis Din,
but who's to say that it'll be a public matter and therefore,
you know, who's going to enforce this idea that he has to
make this נדר? neder? So this is like very, very disturbing. First
of all,
you know, if that's the הלכה halacha that you're supposed to be
ידירנה הנאה, yadirana hana’ah, then even if there is no בית דין,
Beis Din, shouldn't that be how you're acting? What, it should be
the בית דין Beis Din’s responsibility and not like your responsibility to
do this? Number two, probably even more troubling is that, you know,
if רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel wants you to
make this this נדר, neder, then it's obviously saying that there is
something morally wrong with this decision. I mean you would know that
even without רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. You know,
you're doing this whole scheme to get money from the ערב arev
who did you this favor and was the guarantor of your loan
and you're not really planning on divorcing your wife. So there seems
to be, okay, technically he's legally liable, technically you are divorced, but
you know, it's like really that's what we should be doing is
just technically? Like this seems like deeply disturbing on many levels. Let's
see what the גמרא Gemara does. To some degree the גמרא Gemara
asks this question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: וסוף
איגלאי מילתא דכהן הוא. u-sof igla’ei milta de-kohen hu. In the end
it turned out that anyway that this רב הונא Rav Huna the
son of of משה בר עצרי Moshe bar Atzri was a כהן.
kohen. So if he were to divorce his wife he wouldn't be
able to remarry her. So even you know, were he to follow
אביי Abaye’s advice he would get stuck. It wasn't exactly clear whether
that was found out before or after he divorced, hopefully it was
before he divorced his wife. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye
said, היינו דאמרי אינשי בתר עניא אזלא עניותא, hainu de-amri inshi basar
aniya azla aniyusa, poverty follows the poor. The poor get poorer. You
know, ugh, this guy he just has bad luck after bad luck.
Okay, even this advice that I wanted to help him, it isn't
going to help him, he's really stuck. Okay. מי אמר אביי הכי?
Mi amar Abaye hachi? Now we're going to ask how אביי Abaye
could make such a
suggestion. והאמר אביי Veha amar Abaye doesn't אביי Abaye say איזהו רשע
ערום Eizehu rasha arum זה המשיא עצה למכור בנכסים כרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל? Ze hamashi etza limkor b'nechasim k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? This is
a completely different רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, who
it's considered to be a wicked person who is, you know, like,
scheming? Or ערום arum could also mean like, like, clever, you know,
he's successful, but he's doing something bad. This would be somebody who
gives somebody an advice. The הלכה halacha is that if I give
a gift to ראובן Reuven and I say, you know, this field
should be yours, ואחריך לשמעון, v'acharecha l'Shimon, and after you die it
should go on to שמעון. Shimon. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says, if ראובן Reuven were to sell it to a
third party, to לוי, Levi, then it would not go to שמעון.
Shimon. So, and so, and you know, so that would be sort
of like smart for ראובן, Reuven, because ראובן Reuven only has the
use of the field while ראובן Reuven is still alive. If he
goes ahead and he sells it to לוי, Levi, לוי Levi now
gets the field permanently. So, the field is worth more to לוי
Levi than it is to ראובן, Reuven, because ראובן Reuven breaks sort
of the progression of it going from him to שמעון. Shimon. So,
if somebody else were to come and say to ראובן, Reuven, "Hey
ראובן, Reuven, you know, you'd be better off selling this field to
לוי, Levi, getting the full value of the field, and then you'd
be better off with having it just now that you have it
just to use for while you're alive." So ראובן Reuven would be
totally within his rights to do that, but if somebody gives that
advice, they basically are getting involved—this is why you're a רשע rasha
because it's—you're getting involved in a ריב לא לו. riv lo lo.
You know, you—it's not your issue at all, and here you are,
you're interfering in something that's none of your business, and you are
benefiting ראובן Reuven at the expense of שמעון Shimon and against the
wishes of the person who gave this field to ראובן, Reuven, against
my wishes. So you're subverting my wishes to benefit somebody when you
have no interest in it at somebody else's expense. So you should
not be doing things like that even if technically legally it's acceptable.
So here too, אביי Abaye is suggesting that somebody is getting involved
in something that is not his business, and he's going ahead and
trying to give advice, you know, to this—to this what's his name,
this רב הונא, Rav Huna, that he should do something which is
against the whole intent of the ערב arev and is, you know,
and is really hurting the ערב, arev,
and, you know, through this whole deception. So how could you be
doing such a thing, right? How could this be morally acceptable? So
let's take a look, even if it's going to be technically legally
playing by the rules. So the גמרא Gemara says בנו שאני וצורבא
מרבנן שאני. Bno shani v'tzurba m'rabanan shani. No, here
it's not so bad. In the end, who's—who is this רב הונא
Rav Huna going to collect from? He's going to collect from his
father, this משה בר עצרי. Moshe bar Atzri. The father is the
ערב arev for the כתובה. kesubah. So maybe the father doesn't want
to just give his son a loan, maybe the son is even
embarrassed to ask for a loan or doesn't want to give his
son a gift. Okay, but at the end of the day, you're
not taking money out of a family. You know, in the end,
you're passing money from the father to the son. So
like
in this case, it's not the, you know, you're not taking it
from ראובן Reuven and giving it to שמעון Shimon like in the
case of the field, to a total stranger, and you're—and you know,
you're
cheating the intent of the giver. Here you're taking it from a
father and giving it to a son. But okay, but still, that
wasn't why the father agreed to be the ערב. arev. I mean,
maybe—maybe the father doesn't mind so much, you know, but maybe he
does. So that's not so satisfying, that's like, "Oh, it's not so
bad, you know, it's still just going from father to son." That's
answer number one.
And point number two anyway is that even if that wasn't as
much of a diversion of the resources, you know, or of the
property, of the money, this case is a—is much more of a
deception. In the case of selling the field, ראובן Reuven has—is entitled.
He might not know the law, he might not be aware that
he's entitled, it might not be exactly what the gifter wanted to
do, but there's no deception, he's just, you know, pursuing his self-interest.
Here the whole thing is deceitful. So it's very disturbing that the
גמרא Gemara sort of makes its peace with it. I mean, it's
making its peace with it because אביי Abaye said it. But let's
see also the other thing it adds. So number one the גמרא
Gemara says בנו שאני
וצורבא מרבנן שאני. Bno shani v'tzurba m'rabanan shani.
It's also different because this רב הונא Rav Huna was a צורבא
מרבנן. tzurba m'rabanan. So if it's a צורבא מרבנן, tzurba m'rabanan, what's
it—the point? The point is you're allowed to cheat if it's for
the sake of תורה? Torah? That's a really bad message. You know,
maybe the point is is that it wasn't like it wasn't considered
to be not his issue, like something that was none of his
business. It is the business that to try to make sure that
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim can put food on the table. Okay, fine.
So. weren't interfering in something that you had no business interfering in.
But again, none of this really addresses the issue about the deception.
So this really remains, I would say, quite problematic. All right, now
the... but whatever, that's where the גמרא Gemara ends up. Let's continue.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
והא ערב הוא, V'ha arev hu, one minute, how could the father
anyway be on the hook for the כתובה? ketubah? He was an
ערב. arev. וקיימא לן ערב דכתובה לא משתעבד, v'kaimalan arev d'ketubah lo
mishtabed, and we we have a principle which we're about to say
in a few lines, that an ערב arev of a כתובה ketubah
does not really legally liable. Why is he not really legally liable?
Because as we'll see, the person, reason a person would be a
guarantor to sign on for a כתובה ketubah would be to help
the couple get married. But it doesn't really mean and it's not
like a loan where the person borrows money then really owns it
and you're trying to make sure that the lender gets his money
back. Here, no loan is taking place and the person is doing
it just to ensure that the couple get married, so he's not
really serious about his commitment, which is obviously, which is also disturbing
because the real... it might be true that no money is lent,
but the woman is making a decision like to commit her life
to this man. And one of the real things that חז"ל Chazal
instituted the כתובה ketubah was to make sure that her interests were
protected. So, she's not giving over any money, but she's sort of
giving over herself. And if it's important that her interest be protected,
it's important that they be protected. So, you know, that's disturbing, but
it's not that the גמרא Gemara says that it's not important that
she have the כתובה. ketubah. What it's more saying is that this
man probably who decided to be an ערב arev wasn't being serious
about it. We can't assume he's being serious about it. Again, it's
still a bit of a problem that the halakhic system reinforces that
rather than demands that he actually does keep by his commitment. But
the assumption here is you have to go by גמר דעת, g'mar
da'at, and the guy was just throwing it out there to make
move things along with the wedding, not being serious. Okay, now that
says the גמרא Gemara says is how we rule, which is quite
fascinating because it's exactly against our משנה, Mishnah, where רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel absolutely assumes that an ערב arev is
liable, which why he demands to make this vow that you're not
going to get, you know, remarried, you're not going to get any
הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't try to reconcile it
with the משנה, Mishnah, it just says we rule that you really
do not assume this responsibility. So then why in this case did
this ערב arev have that responsibility? והא קיימא לן ve-ha kaimalan that
the גמרא Gemara says ערב דכתובה לא משתעבד, arev d'ketubah lo mishtabed,
that he really does not become encumbered, does not become obligated? קבלן
הוה. Kablan hava.
Oh, he wasn't just an ערב, arev, he was a קבלן, kablan,
which we said yesterday means that he didn't just say 'I'll be
the guarantor,' he'll say, he said, 'It is like I am receiving
the money, I will pay the money.' Here there's no money to
receive, but it's like the debt comes directly to me and I
will pay it. Okay, so in that case, that's why, that's why
it would work even in a case of a כתובה ketubah because
that's a much more serious language. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara is
going to say, one minute, even in that case, it's not clear
that everybody agrees there's an obligation by a כתובה. ketubah. הני ניחא
למאן דאמר קבלן דכתובה אף על גב דלית ליה נכסים לבעל משתעבד
שפיר. Hani nicha l'man d'amar kablan d'ketubah af al gav d'leit lei
nechasim l'baal mishtabed, shapir. That's good according to the opinion, which we'll
see in a minute, that says by קבלן kablan of a כתובה
ketubah that even if the husband has no money, it is the
he is obligated. אלא למאן דאמר אית ליה משתעבד לית ליה לא
משתעבד מאי איכא למימר. Ella l'man d'amar it lei mishtabed, leit lei
lo mishtabed, mai ika l'meimar.
But according to the position that even in a case of a
קבלן kablan by a כתובה, ketubah, he's only obligated if the husband
has money, he's not obligated if the husband doesn't have money. Now
that's a little bit bizarre, right? Because when is the biggest time
when you need a guarantor? When the actual person that you're hoping
to collect from doesn't have the money. That's when you're most insistent
on a guarantor. Here the גמרא Gemara says that when the person
doesn't have money, it might be that you are not obligated. How
is this possible?
So again, this goes back to the question of the דעת, da'at,
of the intent of the ערב. arev. And if the husband doesn't
have money, then they're not going to get married if somebody can't
guarantee the כתובה. ketubah. So in that type of a case, we
say the ערב arev wasn't really serious about it. He was just
saying it in order should get the wedding to take place. Okay.
If the חתן chatan has money, and nobody needed to be an
ערב, arev, and you're stepping in to be an ערב, arev, then
you are serious. So again, the sad part about this is, is
that the more that the person is needed and the more that
this woman might be making a decision based on the fact that
there's a guarantor to the loan and she can't trust that she's
going to get it from the husband, then the more we say
that he might not really have גמר דעת g'mar da'at and he
might not really be obligating himself. Does not sound, I mean I
understand that we have to care about his גמר דעת, g'mar da'at,
but sounds like, you know, the woman is דווקא davka losing out
in the case where... It's most needed. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says, even if we say that a קבלן kablan works for a
כתובה, kesuva, according to one opinion, that's only if the husband has
money. If the husband doesn't have money, a קבלן kablan doesn't work.
And here presumably the husband didn't have money. That was the story.
So how does the being of the קבלן kablan work in this
case? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: איבעית אימא מהוי הוה
ליה ואישתדף. Ibayis eima mehavei hava lei v'ishtadaf. It's possible that this
Rav Huna had money when they got married, and then the property
got like destroyed, you know, or depreciated. So therefore the
קבלן kablan really was obligating himself, the father, and that's why it
would have been possible to go collect because at the time he
really did have money, so the accepting to be a קבלן kablan
was serious. ואיבעית אימא אמלגבי בריה שעבודי משעביד נפשיה. V'ibayis eima amalgabei
brei shibudei m'shabid nafshie. Or here we're going to again invoke the
idea of the father, that because he was the father, his obligation
he really did intend to obligate himself. Even though under normal circumstance
the guy just wants to get the wedding moving along, here because
the money is going to go, you know, it is for the
sake of his son, actually his son's wife, but we feel that,
you know, he really is serious about wanting to put up the
money. Okay, so what the גמרא Gemara now has basically introduced is
against our משנה mishna that sounds like an ערב דכתובה areiv dekesuva
follows the normal rules of an ערב, areiv, the גמרא Gemara has
now said that actually no, an ערב דכתובה areiv dekesuva does not
obligate himself, and even if somebody uses the language of a קבלן,
kablan, even there there's a debate and it might only be binding
if it's a case that the חתן chosson already has resources. So
let's take a look so about how the גמרא Gemara continues with
this question.
דאתמר, De'itmar, because it was taught. Here's the debate we were referencing
just now and let's actually now cite the original source of the
debate. ערב דכתובה, Areiv diksuva, if somebody agrees to be an ערב
areiv of a כתובה, kesuva, דברי הכל לא משתעבד, divei hakol lo
mishtabeid, everybody agrees against our משנה mishna that you are not, you
don't obligate yourself. קבלן דבעל חוב, Kablan deba'al chov, now if you
say you're going to be a קבלן kablan of a debt and
use the language of קבלן, kablan, דברי הכל משתעבד, divei hakol mishtabeid,
then of course קבלן kablan is the stronger language and in a
case of a בעל חוב ba'al chov where money really is changing
hands and you're not just trying to get a couple married, everybody
agrees that the combination of those two definitely the obligation is binding.
So דברי הכל משתעבד. divei hakol mishtabeid. קבלן דכתובה וערב דבעל חוב,
Kablan diksuva v'areiv deba'al chov, however, if it's a mix, you use
the stronger language of קבלן kablan but it's a case of כתובה
kesuva where money isn't changing hands and maybe you're just trying to
get the wedding moving along, so maybe you're not really serious about
it but you use the serious language of קבלן. kablan. Or you're
an ערב areiv and a בעל חוב, ba'al chov, you use the
lighter language of ערב areiv but it is a case of a
בעל חוב ba'al chov of really lending money where the guy's putting
out money because he's expecting to get it back. So in those
middle cases it's a debate, פליגי, pligi, they debate. מר סבר אי
אית ליה נכסי ללוה משתעבד אי לית ליה לא משתעבד. Mar savar
ei is lei nechashei l'loveh mishtabeid, ei leis lei lo mishtabeid. Some
say in those middle cases it only works if the ללוה loveh
has money and then nobody was forcing the בעל חוב ba'al chov
to step, the ערב areiv to step up. And if he stepped
up anyway then he's obligating himself. But if the ללוה loveh did
not have money and nothing would have happened without him, so he's
just saying he's going to do it but he's not really serious
about it and he doesn't obligate himself. Again, now it's not only
not being fair to the woman, it's not being fair to the
creditor. I'm lending this guy money, he didn't have any money, I
was only going to do it because I was expecting to get
my money back, you agreed to do
it and you said you were going to be the ערב. areiv.
But because you knew that I was only going to do it
for that reason, then you were just saying it to get me
to lend the money and you weren't really serious. Like what? I
mean that seems to be making like absolutely no sense that הלכה
halacha should recognize your lack of גמר דעת, gemar das, you know,
given that I am making decisions based on it. So again, very
hard to understand this גמרא. Gemara. Okay, but that's the question. Some
say in these middle cases it only is binding if the person
had money so the ערב areiv doing it was not necessary, so
his doing it is a real obligation. But otherwise it is not
an obligation because he was just doing it to move things along.
ומר סבר, U'mar savar, and the other one holds, בין אית ליה
בין לית ליה משתעבד, bein is lei bein leis lei mishtabeid, that
no,
regardless, you know, even in these middle cases whether the guy has
money or doesn't have money, you said you were going to be
a guarantor, you are obligated. Now what's very strange here is a
couple of things besides the problems I've been flagging. One is, who's
the מר mar and who's the מר? mar? This one holds this
one, this one holds that one. Nobody is named here. We're trying
to finally quote the source of this debate and we have absolutely
no name to position, no name of אמורא. Amora. Right, so like
the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, or the רשב"ם Rashbam says that
it was, no, some אמוראים Amoraim must have debated this but we
don't really even know who was on which side of the debate.
So that's very very strange about that,
about that. The other thing to note is as against the גמרא's
Gemara we've been seeing earlier where the גמרא's Gemara did have questions
about the language of ערב arev or the language of קבלן kablan
in terms of the order in which you can collect, here it's
actually was debated whether an ערב arev even for a loan had
any obligation at all, not just a question about the right like
where you go to first. So very strange the way this discussion,
a, seems to be like not fair to the other side and
against our משנה Mishnah and undercutting some of the points that we
said before and really limiting the situations in which there's an assumption
of liability, of obligation. Okay, but let's see how the גמרא Gemara
concludes.
והלכתא, Vehilchata, on the הלכה halacha is, second wide line, ערב, arev,
when it's a case of ערב arev meaning of all cases of
ערב, arev, whether you use language of ערב, arev, whether you use
language of קבלן, kablan, בין אית ליה בין לית ליה משתעבד. bein
is lei bein leis lei mishtabeid. You know, the person if you
say you're going to be a guarantor, whatever language you use, you're
obligated. Okay, great. That's consistent with what we said before. And the
one so that's saying the middle case is yes you are obligated.
And the one thing that we are carving out is the weaker
language with כתובה. ketubah. Okay, which is except for,
בר מערב דכתובה, bar me'arev dekesubah, except for when you use the
ערב arev language, the weaker language and it's כתובה, ketubah, that is
the one case that we are saying that you're not really serious
and in that case let's see what we let's see, דאף על
גב דאית ליה לבעל לא משתעבד. de'af al gav de'is lei l'ba'al
lo mishtabeid. And in that case, when he used the ערב arev
language, even if the guy has money, because you're using the weaker
language, you're not really serious about assuming your obligation. דאף על גב
דאית ליה לבעל לא משתעבד, af al gav de'is lei l'ba'al lo
mishtabeid, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's reason, מצוה הוא דעביד ולאו מידי
חסרה. mitzvah hu de'aveid velav midi chasrei.
You're just doing a מצוה, mitzvah, you're just trying to get this
nice couple married and the woman nobody is lending out money, the
woman isn't lending out money, so you're just signing on to do
something nice and it's not really serious. Now it could be at
this stage what the גמרא Gemara means is that it was very
pro forma, sort of like we do the תנאים. t'nayim. It was
more like a ritual of signing on to the ערב arev and
nobody took it seriously. If that's true it makes a lot more
sense, that it's an honorific type of a thing to sign on
as the ערב arev but nobody ever really expected that to become
a legal responsibility. I'm not sure the גמרא Gemara is saying that.
But anyway, this strange ruling that goes against what we've been saying
before and does not seem very fair, at least we are limiting
it to the one case of when you both use the weaker
language ערב arev and it's a case of כתובה, ketubah, although we
apply it regardless of whether the guy has money or not. All
right. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna,
says רב הונא, Rav Huna, שכיב מרע שחילק כל נכסיו ואמר מנה
לפלוני בידי נאמן. shechiv mera shechileik kol nechasav ve'amar maneh leploni beyadi
ne'eman. חזקה אין אדם עושה קנוניא על הקדש. Chazaka ein adam oseh
kenunyah al hekdesh. If a שכיב מרע, shechiv mera,
somebody who's on his deathbed, gives all of his money to הקדש,
hekdesh, gives all of his money to charity, but says and then
says but you know, actually a hundred dollars, a hundred זוז zuz
I owe ראובן. Reuven. So that you can't give it all, you
have to separate off a hundred זוז zuz which belongs to ראובן.
Reuven. So then we believe him. נאמן ne'eman he's believed. חזקה אין
אדם עושה קנוניא על הקדש, Chazaka ein adam oseh kenunyah al hekdesh,
right,
we have a presumption, we can take it for granted that you're
not going to try to cheat הקדש. hekdesh. Oh, I want ראובן
Reuven to get the money so even though it belongs to הקדש
hekdesh I'll claim that I owe ראובן Reuven the money. No, nobody's
trying to cheat out הקדש hekdesh so you would be believed and
the heirs would have to pay ראובן. Reuven. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, מתקיף לה רב נחמן, maskif lah Rav
Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman asked on this, וכי אדם עושה
קנוניא על בניו? vechi adam oseh kenunyah al banav?
But one minute, but the same way a person wouldn't want to
cheat out הקדש, hekdesh, we don't think a person would want to
cheat out his children from their inheritance. אבל דרב ושמואל אמרי תרווייהו,
But deRav uShmuel amri tuvai, but רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both
say, שכיב מרע שאמר מנה לפלוני בידי, shechiv mera she'amar maneh leploni
beyadi, so if on his deathbed somebody says I owe ראובן Reuven
a hundred dollars, אמר תנו, amar tenu, if he says and give
it to him, then we take him at his word and we
give ראובן Reuven the hundred dollars. לא אמר תנו, Lo amar tenu,
but if he didn't say give it to him he just said
I owe ראובן Reuven a hundred dollars, אין נותנין. ein nosnim. You
don't give it to ראובן. Reuven. Why not? אלמא אדם עשוי שלא
להשביע את בניו. Almah adam asui shelo lehasbi'a es banav.
So a person acts in a way to make it that his
people shouldn't think his kids are rich. Oh you died, you left
your kids this big inheritance, so he's going to make an announcement,
no, I have plenty of debt, I have a million dollars in
debt to various people so people won't now go and try to
cheat the kids out of their inheritance or think the kids have
all of this money. So unless he says תנו, tenu, he's not
trying to to, you know, cheat his kids and give it to
ראובן Reuven even though ראובן Reuven doesn't deserve it, but he's not,
he's still not serious when he says it because he has another
motivation. He's trying to make it look that his kids are not
rich. So if that's true, how's that relevant here? So here the
גמרא Gemara says as well, הכא נמי hacha nami top of דף
כ"ו עמוד א', daf kaf-vov amud aleph, here as well,
אדם עשוי שלא להשביע את עצמו. adam asui shelo lehasbia et atzmo.
So you want to make yourself not look rich. So if you're
giving all of your money to הקדש, Hekdesh, maybe you'll say, oh,
I owe ראובן Reuven a million dollars, so people don't think, oh,
look at this guy, he's so wealthy, he gave all of his
money to הקדש. Hekdesh. No, in order that people shouldn't think that,
you're making a claim that you owe a million dollars to ראובן,
Reuven, and unless you say תנו, tenu, it's not serious. Now I
have to say this is hard to exactly understand. You understand why
you don't want to make your kids look rich and you're about
to die and people take advantage of them, so people should think
that they have all these outstanding debts. But here,
הקדש Hekdesh is going to get the money and you are about
to die. Why is it important that people think that you're not,
don't look rich? And nobody's going to try to take advantage of
you in your last few days or weeks or whatever because you've
already just gave all your money to הקדש. Hekdesh. So I really
don't, a lot of these, the today's דף, daf, I don't really
understand. But that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So therefore maybe we
should say the same thing, that we don't believe it's true unless
you say תנו. tenu. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says:
כי אמר רב הונא התם דנקיט שטר. ki amar Rav Huna hatam
denakat shtar. No, when
רב הונא Rav Huna said that if you say, you know, I
owe ראובן Reuven a hundred dollars after you sanctified your property to
הקדש, Hekdesh, you're believed, it's when ראובן Reuven has a שטר. shtar.
Now you're probably asking, if ראובן Reuven has a שטר, shtar, why
do I need to say that I owe him the money?
So, you know, it might be that the שטר shtar isn't מקויים,
mekuyam, we'll see that in a minute, but תוספות Tosafot says that
one of the things going on here is that when somebody comes
to collect from orphans, even if he has a שטר shtar and
even if it's מקויים, mekuyam, he has to take a שבועה shvuah
that he hasn't been paid, because the orphans don't know the business
dealings of their father. So even though if somebody comes to me
with a שטר, shtar, right, I'm not believed to say that I
paid it because he has a שטר מקויים, shtar mekuyam, what's my
proof that I paid it? But if it's a case of orphans,
the guy even with the שטר shtar needs to make a שבועה.
shvuah. But if the father on his deathbed said, I owe the
money, then he doesn't need to make a שבועה. shvuah. So that's
why, since you've already got the שטר, shtar, this person is believed
and it relieves the creditor of the need to make a שבועה.
shvuah. So כי אמר רב הונא התם דנקיט שטר. ki amar Rav
Huna hatam denakat shtar. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מכלל
דרב ושמואל דלא נקיט שטר? michlal deRav uShmuel delo nakat shtar? So
when רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel said that if a person says he
owes ראובן Reuven money and he doesn't say תנו, tenu, he's not
believed on, you know, on his deathbed, right, that's a case where
ראובן Reuven doesn't have a שטר? shtar? But how could that be?
אמר תנו נותנין. amar tenu notnin. So in that case if you
would say תנו, tenu, you would give it, and if they're talking
about a scenario that the guy didn't have a שטר, shtar, but
מלווה על פה הוי, malveh al peh havei, with no שטר, shtar,
it's a loan, you know, it's a loan on oral loan, a
loan without a שטר, shtar, and אינה גובה לא מן היתומים ולא
מן הלקוחות. einah goveh lo min hayetomim velo min halakuchot. And the
principle is that on an oral, you know, a loan that doesn't
have a שטר, shtar, you cannot collect from the orphans or from,
you know, buyers, right, because there's no שיעבוד, shebud, there's no lien.
So if that's true, right, we always have to be talking about
a שטר. shtar. Without a שטר, shtar,
nobody would ever collect from the orphans. So if the same way
רב הונא Rav Huna is talking about a שטר shtar and the
guy is believed and ראובן Reuven doesn't have to make a שבועה,
shvuah, so in רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel as well, you know, the
guy must have a שטר shtar or else he wouldn't be able
to collect from orphans. So why isn't the person who said that
he owed ראובן Reuven the money believed when he says it on
his deathbed? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says: אלא אמר
רב נחמן, ella amar Rav Nachman, says רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, אידי
ואידי דנקיט שטר. idi ve'idi denakat shtar. Fine, both of them the
cases is that ראובן Reuven has a שטר. shtar. ולא קשיא הא
דמקויים הא דלא מקויים. velo kashya had mekuyam had lo mekuyam. In
the case of,
you know, the first case of הקדש, Hekdesh, ראובן Reuven has a
שטר shtar that is מקויים, mekuyam, that actually the signatures have been
verified.
So there's, so the only thing left for is for ראובן Reuven
to have to make the שבועה shvuah that it hasn't been paid.
So in that case, if the guy on his deathbed said, after
he was מקדיש makdish his property, that I owe ראובן Reuven the
money, the debt is still outstanding, even without the תנו, tenu, that
alleviates, you know, relieves ראובן Reuven of the responsibility to make the
שבועה. shvuah. That's when he's already coming with a hundred percent ironclad
שטר. shtar. And then the guy saying it on his deathbed is
enough. Okay. הא דלא מקויים, had lo mekuyam, but in the case
of רב ושמואל, Rav uShmuel, ראובן's Reuven שטר shtar is not מקויים.
mekuyam. And in that case, you normally, he would have to establish,
you know, be מקיים mekayem the signatures. So saying that the שכיב
מרע shchiv meira said he owed the money does not, is not
enough to relieve from ראובן Reuven the obligation to be מקיים mekayem
the שטר. shtar. Only if you said תנו, tenu, you know, now
you now then he says now ראובן Reuven doesn't have to. Doesn't
have to make a שבועה, shevuah, doesn't have to be מקיים mekayem
the שטר. shtar. But without that ראובן Reuven still would have to
be מקיים mekayem the שטר. shtar.
So we've come very far from the original statement that we just
trust a guy, he's not going to cheat הקדש hekdesh etc. Now,
it's like all of the evidence is already there. ראובן Reuven has
the שטר, shtar, you know, and it's מקויים. mekuyam. And the only
point is that if he says I owe him the money even
without תנו, tnu, once it's already a שטר מקויים, shtar mekuyam, you
don't have to make a שבועה. shevuah.
But if it wasn't a שטר מקויים, shtar mekuyam, you would have
to say תנו. tnu. Without תנו, tnu, not only do you have
to- not without תנו, tnu, you have to be מקיים mekayem it,
okay? But with תנו, tnu, you don't have to be מקיים mekayem
it. That's what we now wind up saying, not at all what
these earlier statements actually sounded like. I should also, by the way,
mention that as a matter of הלכה, halacha, we actually פוסקן pasken
that even a מלווה על פה milveh al peh can collect from
יורשים. yorshim. That was something that got established after the גמרא Gemara
at the time of the גאונים, Geonim, and that allows, you know,
for at least people that have outstanding- the creditors to not totally
lose out their money. Alright, so that's important to know. Let's continue.
אמר רב פפא, אמר תנו,
הן מקויים הן לא מקויים. Amar Rav Pappa, amar tnu, hen mekuyam
hen lo mekuyam. אמר תנו קיימיה לשטריה. Amar tnu kayeimei l'shatrei. So
in a case of a שטר shtar אינו מקויים, eino mekuyam, that's
why the שכיב מרע shchiv meira had to say תנו. tnu. By
saying תנו, tnu, it's effectively a קיום kiyum of the שטר. shtar.
לא אמר תנו לא קיימיה לשטריה, Lo amar tnu lo kayeimei l'shatrei,
but without it it is not a קיום kiyum of the שטר.
shtar. Alright, and even though he says he owes the money, it's
not enough, maybe he's doing it שלא להשביע את בניו, shelo lehasbia
es banav, not to make his kids look rich, and therefore קיום
kiyum of a שטר shtar is still needed.
Fine. New point. אמר רבא, שכיב מרע שאמר מנה לפלוני בידי ואמרו
יתומים פרענו. Amar Rava, shchiv meira she'amar maneh l'ploni biyadi v'amru yetomim
paranu. So שכיב מרע shchiv meira says I owe ראובן Reuven money
and the יתומים yetomim say yeah, but we paid it up. Now,
the question is it sounds very much like the previous case and
are we talking about with a שטר shtar because the previous case
we said we were talking about a שטר? shtar? So here the
ראשונים Rishonim explain that we are talking about a case, not necessarily
whatever with the whole issue before or on the same parameters, but
we are talking about a case where the guy, ראובן, Reuven, actually
demanded his money and the שכיב מרע shchiv meira admitted it. Okay,
so that's like a different type of a scenario.
And then afterwards the orphans said that we actually paid it up.
ואמרו יתומים פרענו, v'amru yetomim paranu, נאמנים. ne'emanin. I'm sorry, did I
skip a line? אמר רבא, שכיב מרע שאמר מנה לפלוני בידי ואמרו
יתומים פרענו. Amar Rava, shchiv meira she'amar maneh l'ploni biyadi v'amru yetomim
paranu. So if he just says that
he
owes the money, then the- then the orphans are believed to say
we paid it up, okay, after the father died or the father
paid after he said it or whatever. נאמנים. ne'emanin. תנו מנה לפלוני,
Tnu maneh l'ploni, but if he said give the hundred dollars to
that
person and then they say we paid it up, אי נאמנים, ei
ne'emanin, they're not believed. Now, we already know that the idea of
תנו tnu more makes it clear that the money is really owed
when it's said by a שכיב מרע, shchiv meira, but the גמרא
Gemara says, but this distinction about their ability to say we paid
it up, that doesn't make sense that that's a function of whether
he said תנו. tnu. So the גמרא Gemara says כלפי לייא? klapi
laya? Like, where's this going? It's the opposite makes sense. איפכא מסתברא,
Ipcha mistabra, the opposite makes sense. אמר תנו מנה, Amar tnu maneh,
if he says give the money, כיון דפסקא אבוהון למילתא, keivan d'paska
avuhon l'milsa, since he made it very clear he commanded them to
give the money, איכא למימר דפרעו, ika l'meimar d'para, then it's more-
you can more assume they listened to him and they paid it
up. Okay. מנה לפלוני בידי, Maneh l'ploni biyadi, he says I owe
him a hundred dollars and he didn't command them to give it,
כיון דלא פסקא אבוהון למילתא, keivan d'lo paska avuhon l'milsa, since he
did not exactly command the matter, you know, direct- direct them, so
איכא למימר דלא פרעו, ika l'meimar d'lo para, maybe they didn't pay
them, right? If anything it makes sense, since you said that without
the תנו tnu
it's more questionable their obligation, then they should be less believed to
say that they paid. The more תנו tnu is a stronger emphasis
that there exists an obligation and it's a stronger directive to them,
then the more they- then the more they should be believed that
they have paid. So because תנו tnu is stronger to establish the
debt and to create that directive, they דוקא davka should be believed.
Without the תנו tnu they shouldn't be believed to say that they
paid. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אלא אי איתמר
הכי איתמר. Ela i itmar hachi itmar. Fine. If it was said,
it was said the following way, a little bit of the reverse.
שכיב מרע שאמר מנה לפלוני בידי ואמרו יתומים חזר ואמר לנו אבא
פרעתי, shchiv meira she'amar maneh l'ploni biyadi v'amru yetomim chazar v'amar lanu
aba parati, נאמנים. ne'emanin. If a שכיב מרע shchiv meira says I
owe a guy a hundred dollars and he didn't say give it
to him. And then, so- and then the orphans say not we
paid. Okay. They say, oh, afterwards our father told us that he
had remembered or you know that he had paid. He either paid
after he told us he owed the money, or he told us
he had remembered afterwards that he had paid. So in that case
the father is the one that says that I've paid.
חזר ואמר אבא פרעתי. Chazar v'amar aba parati. So in that case
נאמנים. ne'emanin. and they're believed. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*? אידכורי מידכר *Itkurei
midkar* because he remembered. He said, "I owe the guy a hundred
dollars," but it wasn't like, "Oh, go pay
him." So he's recalling and then he remembered differently. אידכורי מידכר *Itkurei
midkar*. תנו מנה לפלוני ואמרו יתמי חזר ואמר
אבא פרעתי
*Tnu mane li-ploni v-amru yasmi hazar v-amar Abba parati*. But if he
says "Give," and then they say the father said that the father
said that he had already paid, in that case, אין נאמנין *Ein
ne'emanin*. Then they're not believed that the father said, "Oh, I remember
that I already paid him." Why? דאי איתא דפרע לא הוה אמר
תנו *D'im ita d'para lo hava amar Tnu*. Because, and again, it
sounds like he's saying the father didn't say afterwards he paid, the
father said that after he told us to give, he remembered that
he had already paid. So in that case, they're not believed because
if he
really was uncertain, he never would have been as black and white
as about saying תנו *Tnu*. So again, saying תנו *Tnu* is an
absolutely more certain—because it's more certain and more of a directive, the
orphans are not believed to say they paid... excuse me, because it's
more of a directive, the orphans are believed to say they acted
on that directive and they paid. They would be... if it was
only saying that "I owe the person," they'd be less believed to
say they acted on that directive. So that's the case of when
the orphans are claiming it. But if now the orphans are claiming
not that they paid, but our father remembered that he had already
paid, that's when then it reverses. תנו *Tnu*, which is more of
an absolute debt and more of a directive, the father wouldn't have
said that if he was uncertain. If he said מנה לפלוני *Mane
li-ploni*, it could be he was uncertain and then he remembered and
then he reversed himself. So let's just read that again. תנו מנה
לפלוני ואמרו יתמי חזר ואמר אבא פרעתי אין נאמנין *Tnu mane li-ploni
v-amru yasmi hazar v-amar Abba parati ein ne'emanin*. If the father said,
"Give it," and then they said the father, our father said, "Oh,
I remember that I'd already paid it off," in that case they're
not believed. דאי איתא דפרע לא הוה אמר תנו *D'im ita d'para
lo hava amar Tnu*. If he had really paid, it's not possible
he would have said "Give," "Give it." He wouldn't have been mistaken.
When he says תנו *Tnu*, it means that he clearly, absolutely remembered
and therefore they're not believed to say that he then afterwards realized
he had made a mistake. Okay. So just to finish this up,
בעי רבא *Ba'ei Rava*. רבא *Rava* asks, שכיב מרע שהודה מהו *Shchivmera
she-hoda mahu*? So if a שכיב מרע *Shchivmera* admits that he owes
money to somebody, somebody says "You owe me money," and he says
"Yes, I do," normally we say that that admission is not binding
in court unless he says specifically, "You, Reuven and Shimon, be witnesses
to see that I'm admitting that I owe money." Otherwise, he could
just be saying it to brush the guy off and we don't
take it seriously. But what if it's a case of a שכיב
מרע *Shchivmera*? So שכיב מרע שהודה מהו *Shchivmera she-hoda mahu*? צריך לומר
אתם עדי *Tzarich lomar atem edai*? Does he have to say "You
be my witnesses," and otherwise we say he's not being serious? או
אין צריך לומר אתם עדי *O ein tzarich lomar atem edai*? Or
does he not have to? צריך שיאמר כתבו או אין צריך לומר
כתבו *Tzarich she-yomar ktovu o ein tzarich lomar ktovu*? Also, can you
write up an admission as a שטר shtar *shtar* and turn it
into a שטר shtar *shtar*? Normally you would have to command the
witnesses to say "Write it down as a שטר shtar *shtar*." But
in the case of a שכיב מרע *Shchivmera*, do you have to
do that or not? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, או אין צריך
לומר כתבו *o ein tzarich lomar ktovu*. אדם משטה בשעת מיתה או
אין אדם משטה בשעת מיתה *Adam mashatei b'sha'at mita o ein adam
mashatei b'sha'at mita*? Are we concerned that a person would be like
kidding around, brushing the guy off at the time of the death?
Or do we assume if he's a שכיב מרע *Shchivmera* and he's
admitting it, then he really means it and we don't need him
to do these other to say אתם עדי *atem edai*? And the
גמרא *Gemara* concludes, בתר דבעי הדר פשטה *batar d'ba'ei hadar pashatei*. After
he raised the question, he came to the conclusion, אין אדם משטה
בשעת מיתה *ein adam mashatei b'sha'at mita*. A person does not kid
around at the time of death, and if he admits that he
owes the money, we take that as binding. And similarly, דברי שכיב
מרע ככתובים וכמסורים דמי *divrei Shchivmera k-ktuvin u-k-mesurin dami*. The same way
we say that when שכיב מרע *Shchivmera* says something, it's like it's
written down and it's like he did a קנין *kinyan*, that means
that a שכיב מרע *Shchivmera*'s words have greater weight, and in a
similar way, he does not have to give a specific directive to
write the שטר shtar *shtar*, you can automatically write it as a
שטר *shtar*. Okay. So that is the conclusion of some of these
things a שכיב מרע *Shchivmera* does at the end where he admits
that he owes money. We'll just end with the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
and then finish the מסכת *masechet* tomorrow. המלוה חבירו בשטר גובה מנכסים
משועבדים *Ha-malveh chavero b-shtar goveh mi-nechasim m'shubadim*. If somebody lends money with
a שטר *shtar*, that creates a lien on properties. This is things
we've been assuming all along. And then he can go ahead and
collect the property even after it is sold to other people. He
can collect from encumbered property. על ידי עדים גובה מנכסים בני חורין
goveh minechasim bnei chorin, *Al yedei edim goveh mi-nechasim bnei chorin*. However,
if it's witnesses without a שטר *shtar*, that does not create liens
and he only can collect from unencumbered property, property that's in the
hands of the לוה *loveh* and not property that has been sold.
That's two points. Number one is that you need the שטר *shtar*
to create the public nature of it and to create the שעבודים
*shibudim*. Maybe the שטר *shtar* actually works to actually be a form
of a קנין *kinyan* to create the liens, but certainly the public
nature. And the other thing that it's informing you is even though
the שטר *shtar* doesn't explicitly say that there are liens, we say
אחריות טעות סופר *achrayut ta'ut sofer* and those come automatically with the
שטר *shtar*. הוציא עליו כתב ידו *Hotzi alav ktav yado* she-hu top
of קע"ה עמוד ב' *kuf ayin heh amud bet*. הוציא עליו כתב
ידו שהוא חייב Chayav. לו גובה מנכסים בני חורין. If somebody takes
out a written IOU, I ראובן Reuven owe you שמעון Shimon a
hundred dollars, then that written
IOU can be used as evidence to make me if I'm ראובן
Reuven pay up, but it is not a public שטר with witnesses,
so you cannot use it to collect encumbered property, you could only
use it to collect unencumbered property, property that has not been sold.
ערב היוצא לאחר חיתום שטרות. Arev hayotzei le'achar chitum shtaros. Now let's
say after the שטר has been signed, the guarantor put his obligation
on the שטר underneath the signature of the witnesses. In that case,
גובה מנכסים בני חורין, the creditor if he's collecting from the ערב
arev can only collect from the unencumbered property, but he does not
have lien and he cannot collect from property that the ערב arev
has sold. Why is that? מעשה בא Ma'aseh ba because he did
it
after the witnesses signed so it doesn't have the public nature that
comes through the signing of
witnesses. So it's like it was oral, it's like it was not
in an official שטר because it did not have the witnesses sign
after. If witnesses do sign after, then it creates liens on the
ערב's arev property. מעשה בא לפני רבי ישמעאל ואמר גובה מנכסים בני
חורין. Ma'aseh ba lifnei Rabi Yishmael v'amar goveh minechasim bnei chorin. So
a case like this came to רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael and רבי
ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael said fine, you can collect from the property in
the hands of the ערב arev but not from property that he's
sold. אמר לו בן ננס. Amar lo Ben Nanas. בן ננס Ben
Nanas said to him, אינו גובה לא מנכסים משועבדים ולא מנכסים בני
חורין. Eino goveh lo minechasim meshubadim v'lo minechasim bnei chorin. No,
in that case that he signed after the document was done and
after the loan was made, the ערב arev is completely off the
hook, you can't collect from the ערב arev at all. אמר לו
למה. Amar lo lama. So רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael said to him
why? אמר לו הרי החונק את חבירו בשוק. Amar lo harei hachonek
es chaveiro bashuk. Let's say somebody was choking someone in the marketplace,
ומצאו חבירו, umtza'o chaveiro, and somebody saw what was happening, ואמר לו
הנח לו, ve'amar lo hanach lo, stop choking this guy, ואני אתן
לך, va'ani eten lach, and I'll give you a hundred dollars to
stop choking the guy, פטור, patur, then you'd be exempt because he's
obviously doesn't really want to give the guy a hundred dollars, he's
only trying to protect him. שלא על מנת כן הלווהו, Shelo al
m'nas ken hilvahu, because it's not like I
said go, so now we're sort of translating it to the case
of the loan. When a person becomes a ערב arev after the
loan was made,
then the person who's lending the money is not doing it on
the promise of the creditor. And maybe the guy's only agreeing to
be a creditor, so if I'm intervening after the loan and the
money changed hands, and I'm trying to get you to stop the
מלווה malve to stop giving ראובן Reuven such a hard time and
stop putting so much pressure on. So I'm trying to do it
to help out ראובן Reuven from the
pressure but
you did not actually lend him money because of my promise. And
therefore, you cannot now come to me in order to get paid
up. Only when you take money out of your pocket partly because
I am guaranteeing the loan, that's when you're allowed to come to
me. שלא על מנת כן הלווהו, Shelo al m'nas ken hilvahu, אמונתו
הלווהו. emunaso hilvahu. He did not lend him the money because of
the trust that he was having that he could collect. אלא איזהו
ערב שהוא חייב? Ela eizehu arev shehu chayav? What's the case of
an ערב arev that's obligated? הלווהו ואני נותן לך. Halvahu va'ani noten
lach. Lend him the money and I will pay you. חייב. chayav.
Then you're חייב. שכן על אמונתו הלווהו. Sheken al emunaso hilvahu. In
that case, the money was lent because I was believing I put
my hand in my pocket and I lent the money because I
was believing I could come back to you. And that creates an
obligation, not when you come in later in the process. ואמר רבי
ישמעאל, Ve'amar Rabi Yishmael, and now we end the last משנה in
the last in the end of the בבות, Bavas, רבי ישמעאל Rabi
Yishmael says, הרוצה שיחכים יעסוק בדיני ממונות. Harotzeh sheyachkim ya'asok b'dinei mamanos.
Someone who wants to be smart should involve themselves in the learning
of civil law, דיני ממונות, dinei mamanos, שאין לך מקצוע בתורה יותר
מהן. she'ein lach miktzoa baTorah yoser mehen. There is no field in
תורה Torah that
demands more intellectual
capacity and sharpens your mind more than the study of דיני ממונות.
dinei mamanos. והן כמעיין הנובע. V'hen k'mayan hanove'a. They're like a flowing
well, there's always new ideas. והרוצה שיעסוק בדיני ממונות, V'harotzeh sheya'asok b'dinei
mamanos, and if you want to do דיני ממונות, dinei mamanos, ישמש
את שמעון בן ננס, yeshamesh es Shimon Ben Nanas, then you should
really
attend to שמעון בן ננס Shimon Ben Nanas because he really has
like a lot of not just book smarts, but wisdom, and he's
the one that you really want to learn with and from. Okay,
we will end with that now.